Agriculture & Farming Collection 0007.003.004
Jewish Historical Society of Greater Hartford
Agriculture & Farming
1890-2006
0007.003.004
Jewish Historical Society of Greater Hartford
4.0 Cubic feet 4 document boxes and 1 document box of photographs
With deteriorating conditions in Eastern Europe, many Jews came to the United States with the dream of becoming farmers. Various charities, especially the Baron de Hirsch Fund provided guidance and support and Jewish farming communities appear throughout Connecticut. Many small farms eventually developed into hotels and resorts. This collection documents the Jewish farming community in the Greater Hartford area through family and oral histories, records, newspaper articles, and photographs.
Many Jews immigrated to the Eastern United States towards the end of the nineteenth century specifically to become farmers. Although these new settlers were financed by a variety of philanthropies, most of the funding in New England was provided by the Baron de Hirsh Fund. The Baron, along with many of his contemporaries, believed that Jews should embrace agriculture in order to combat the stereotype of the exclusively urban Jew. Successive waves of immigrants would arrive whenever conditions for Jews deteriorated in Europe or Russia. Many of these Jews sought a healthful life in farming as an antidote to the terrible experiences they had endured in their places of origin. As a result, Jewish farming communities and synagogues emerged throughout Connecticut. The extensive involvement of Connecticut Jewry in the development of New England farming and related enterprises is usually forgotten. Offshoots of Jewish farms included small family hotels and other resorts. Some farms eventually evolved into large and prosperous businesses such as the Connecticut Packing Company (Copaco). Although the nature of farming changed significantly towards the end of the twentieth century, in 2000 many Connecticut farms were still in the hands of descendants of their original owners. It is fortunate for historians that so much of the material in this collection was assembled and preserved. Most of the material in this collection was generated as a result of a survey of Jewish farms in Connecticut jointly undertaken in 1995-1998 by the Jewish Historical Society of Greater Hartford and the Connecticut Historical Commission. Other material related to Jewish farms in Connecticut has been added since that time. The collection includes photographs of individual farms, farmers, and farm buildings, oral histories, and newspaper articles regarding local farm families and businesses. See also: "A Life of the Land: Connecticut's Jewish Farmers", a journal published by the Society.
Arrangement note
Photographs: see Farming Photographs listing
Oral History: see both Family History and Oral History with each town.
Connecticut Historical Commission Survey
A survey of Jewish farms in Connecticut was jointly undertaken in 1995-1998 by the Jewish Historical Society of Greater Hartford and the Connecticut Historical Commission. This series contains documents related to that survey, including administrative documents, photographs, survey forms, and the final published report.
More information related to individual towns may be found in the Towns series.
Abrahms, Bernard; Abrahms, David N.; Adler, David; Adler, Ruth; Bailey, Christopher; Benson, Seymour; Bercowetz, Irving; Cohen, George H.; Cutler, Belle; Einhorn, Sidney Harry; Feinsilver, Alexander; Getthoff, Alexander; Goldberg, Bernard; Goldberg, Robert S.; Gordon, Morton L.; Gottlieb, Leonard; Himmelstein, Rachel; Kavalier, Helena; Kline, Dana L.; Laufer, Jacob; Laufer, Sarah; Levine; Liverant, Zeke; Minch, Boris; Schneider, David; Schneider, Judith Dember; Schwartz, Adam; Schwartz, Stephen; Scott, Edward; Slovkin, Esther Dember; Solomon, Arthur; Squires, Jerome; Weisman, Seymour; Zagray, Harry; Zupnich, Arthur; Colchester, CT; Connecticut Historical Commision Survey; Ellington, CT; Farming; Lebanon, CT; Libson, CT; Manchester, CT; Moodus, CT; Storrs, CT; Windsor, CT
- Connecticut Historical Commission Survey
  - Connecticut Historical Commission Survey/Administration/Correspondence, memos, etc., 1996, 1996-1996
  - Connecticut Historical Commission Survey/Administration/Miscellaneous notes and lists, 1990s, 1990-2000
  - Connecticut Historical Commission Survey/Administration/names of people contacted on note cards, undated
  - Connecticut Historical Commission Survey/Administration/Questionnaire soliciting information, 1995, 1995-1995
  - Connecticut Historical Commission Survey/Administration/Survey forms, duplicates, undated
  - Connecticut Historical Commission Survey/Final report/Cunningham, Janice P. and Ransom, David F., Back to the Land: Jewish Farms and Resorts in Connecticut (1890-1945), 1998
  - Connecticut Historical Commission Survey/Final report/Cunningham, Janice P. and Ransom, David F., undated
- Connecticut Historical Commission Survey
  - Connecticut Historical Commission Survey/Programs and lectures/Ransom, David F., Back to the Land: Jewish Farms and Resorts in Connecticut (1890-1945), Lecture notes., undated
  - Connecticut Historical Commission Survey/Programs and Lectures/flyers re: programs on Jewish farmers in Connecticut, 1980s-2000s, undated
  - Connecticut Historical Commission Survey/Towns/Bozrah, undated
  - Connecticut Historical Commission Survey/Towns/Colchester/123 Broadway, formerly Fairview House, undated
  - Connecticut Historical Commission Survey/Towns/Colchester/156 Hall Hill Road, formerly Dember's Hotel, undated
  - Connecticut Historical Commission Survey/Towns/Colchester/24 Broadway, Reverend Samuel G. Willard House, undated
  - Connecticut Historical Commission Survey/Towns/Colchester/376 Hall's Hill Road, formerly Hershatter's Inn, undated
  - Connecticut Historical Commission Survey/Towns/Colchester/5 Levy Road, formerly Levy's Grandview House, undated
  - Connecticut Historical Commission Survey/Towns/Colchester/520 Lebanon Ave., Nidzon Farm, undated
  - Connecticut Historical Commission Survey/Towns/Colchester/58 Chestnut Hill Road, Becky Meizler farm, undated
  - Connecticut Historical Commission Survey/Towns/Colchester/8 Cato Corner Road, John Sablitz House, undated
  - Connecticut Historical Commission Survey/Towns/Colchester/87 Mill Street, Formerly Zion Hall, undated
  - Connecticut Historical Commission Survey/Towns/Colchester/91 Marvin Road/William Harvey House, undated
  - Connecticut Historical Commission Survey/Towns/Colchester/Liverant & sons Antiques, undated
  - Connecticut Historical Commission Survey/Towns/Colombia/42 pine Street, formerly Angushire Farm, undated
  - Connecticut Historical Commission Survey/Towns/Colombia/477 Route 66, Kassman Farm, undated
  - Connecticut Historical Commission Survey/Towns/Colombia/519 Route 87, Kaplan Farm, undated
  - Connecticut Historical Commission Survey/Towns/Coventry, undated
  - Connecticut Historical Commission Survey/Towns/East Haddam-Moodus/North Moodus Road, formerly Orchard Mansion, undated
  - Connecticut Historical Commission Survey/Towns/East Haddam-Moodus/Miscellaneous, undated
  - Connecticut Historical Commission Survey/Towns/East Haddam-Moodus/Banner Road, Joymax Farm, undated
  - Connecticut Historical Commission Survey/Towns/East Hampton/Chatham Apartments, undated
  - Connecticut Historical Commission Survey/Towns/East Lyme-Niantic, undated
  - Connecticut Historical Commission Survey/Towns/Ellington, undated
  - Towns/Colchester Part I
    - Towns/Colchester/Family History/Benson, Seymour/oral history transcript, 2006, 2006-2006
    - Towns/Colchester/Family History/Einhorn, Sidney Harry, undated
    - Towns/Colchester/Family History/Goldberg, Robert S., 1980s, 1980-1990
    - Towns/Colchester/Family History/Levine, undated
    - Towns/Colchester/Family History/Liverant, Zeke, undated
    - Towns/Colchester/Family History/Solomon, Arthur, undated
    - Towns/Colchester/Family History/Zagray, Harry, 2000, 2000-2000
    - Towns/Colchester/Historical and Architectural Survey, 1991. Note this Survey was conducted earlier than and should not be confused with the statewide survey conducted during 1995-1998., 1991-1991
    - Towns/Colchester/local community/ Ahavath Achim congregation, 1960s-1980s, 1960-1990
    - Towns/Colchester/Miscellaneous information, undated
    - Towns/Colchester/Miscellaneous photocopies, 1890s-1920s, 1890-1930
    - Towns/Colchester/Newspaper articles/Aron, Jeannette Stern, undated
    - Towns/Colchester/Newspaper articles/miscellaneous, undated
    - Towns/Colchester/Oral History/Abrams, Rabbi David, 1986, 1986-1986
    - Towns/Colchester/Oral History/Abrams-Fine, Bernice Gitlin, 1986, 1986-1986
    - Towns/Colchester/Oral History/Adler, David and Ruth, 1986, 1986-1986
    - Towns/Colchester/Oral History/Bailey, Christopher, interviewer, typed notes from various interviews, 1986, 1986-1986
    - Towns/Colchester/Oral History/Benson, Seymour, 1986, 1986-1986
    - Towns/Colchester/Oral History/Cohen, George L., 1986, 1986-1986
    - Towns/Colchester/Oral History/Cohen, Rubin, 1986, 1986-1986
    - Towns/Colchester/Oral History/Getthoff, Alexander, 1986, 1986-1986
    - Towns/Colchester/Oral History/Goldberg, Bernard, 1986, 1986-1986
    - Check: Towns/Colchester/Oral History/Goldman, Robert, 1985-1986, 1986-1986
    - Towns/Colchester/Oral History/Gottlieb, Leonard, 1,1986, 1986-1986
    - Towns/Colchester/Oral History/Himmelstein, Rachel, 1986, 1986-1986
    - Towns/Colchester/Oral History/Laufer, Jacob and Sarah, 1986, 1986-1986
    - Towns/Colchester/Oral History/Liverant, Zeke, 1986, 1986-1986
    - Towns/Colchester/Oral History/Minch, Boris, 1986, 1986-1986
    - Towns/Colchester/Oral History/Schneider, Judith (Dember) and David, 1986, 1986-1986
    - Towns/Colchester/Oral History/Schwartz, Stephen, 1986, 1986-1986
    - Towns/Colchester/Oral History/Scott, Edward, n.d., 1986-1986
    - Towns/Colchester/Oral History/Slovkin, Esther Dember, 1986, 1986-1986
    - Towns/Colchester/Oral History/Squires, Jerome, 1986, 1986-1986
    - Towns/Colchester/Oral History/Stula, Michael, 1986, 1986-1986
    - Towns/Colchester/Oral History/Zupnich, Arthur, 1986, 1986-1986
    - Towns/Colchester/Oral History/Release Forms signed by interviewees, undated
    - Towns/Colchester/Oral History Project/ Mrs. Mehl and the Chicken Hawk, 1986, 2 folders, 1986-1986
    - Towns/Colchester/Oral History Project/ Mrs. Mehl and the Chicken Hawk, videotape, 1986, 1986-1986
- Connecticut Historical Commission Survey
  - Connecticut Historical Commission Survey/Towns/Glastonbury, undated
  - Connecticut Historical Commission Survey/Towns/Hebron, undated
  - Connecticut Historical Commission Survey/Towns/Killingly-Danielson-Dayville, undated
  - Connecticut Historical Commission Survey/Towns/Lebanon, undated
  - Connecticut Historical Commission Survey/Towns/Lisbon-Griswold-Jewett City, undated
  - Connecticut Historical Commission Survey/Towns/Manchester, undated
  - Connecticut Historical Commission Survey/Towns/Mansfield, undated
  - Connecticut Historical Commission Survey/Towns/Marlborough, undated
  - Connecticut Historical Commission Survey/Towns/Montville, undated
  - Connecticut Historical Commission Survey/Towns/North Branford, undated
  - Connecticut Historical Commission Survey/Towns/Plainville-Moosup, undated
  - Connecticut Historical Commission Survey/Towns/Preston, undated
  - Connecticut Historical Commission Survey/Towns/Salem, undated
  - Connecticut Historical Commission Survey/Towns/Windham, undated
- Connecticut Historical Commission Survey/Ransom, David, lecture photos and notes, 1996, undated
  - Connecticut Historical Commission Survey
- Connecticut State: Jewish farming in the state of Connecticut as a whole
  - Connecticut Humanities Council/Barn Again! Celebrating an America Icon/Exhibit, 2005
  - Connecticut State/Miscellaneous newspaper articles, undated
  - Connecticut State/Published material/In Touch with the Land: Images of Connecticut Farm Life, 1937-1985, booklet, 1985, 1937-1945
  - Connecticut State/Miscellaneous, undated
  - Connecticut State/Research Papers/Libo, Kenneth Back to the Land: Pioneer Connecticut Jewish Farm Families, undated
  - Connecticut Historical Commission Survey/Research Papers/Rosanno, Geoffrey L. Historic Preservation in Connecticut: Volume IV: Western Uplands: Historical and Architectural Overview and Management Guide. Connecticut Historical Commission State historic Preservation Office, 1996, Excerpts, undated
  - Connecticut Jewish History: Journal of the Connecticut Jewish Historical Society of Greater Hartford, undated
  - Connecticut Jewish History/Materials, including disks for planned issue on farming, undated
- Towns
  - Towns/Bloomfield/Farmers/Bercowetz, Kalmen (Copaco) unloading cattle, 1930s, undated
  - Towns/Bloomfield/Farmers/Rostow, Sarah, 1913, undated
  - Towns/Chesterfield/Synagogue, undated
  - Towns/Colchester/Farmers/Dembers family and farm, 1920s, undated
  - Towns/Colchester/Farmers/Gitlin, Samuel and Sarah, undated
  - Towns/Colchester/Farmers/Goldman, Robert, 1966, undated
  - Towns/Colchester/Farmers/Miscellaneous snapshots, mostly labeled, collected for “Colchester Experience” exhibit, 1980s-1930, undated
  - Towns/Colchester/Farmers/unidentified, see Over I, People/Farmers, undated
  - Towns/Colchester/Local Community/Bacon Academy graduating class, 1908, undated
  - Towns/Colchester/Local Community/SS Leather Co (Schwartz and Schwartz), c. 1910, undated
  - Towns/Colchester/Miscellaneous scenes/labeled/Abrams, Beatrice photographer, 1990s, undated
  - Towns/Colchester/Miscellaneous scenes/unlabeled, reproductions made in 1986, undated
  - Towns/Colchester/Miscellaneous scenes/unlabeled/Bailey, Chris, photographer, 1986, undated
  - Towns/Colchester/Oral History/Levin, Mildred, 1986, undated
  - Towns/Colchester/postcards and reproductions of postcards, undated
  - Towns/Colchester/Weisman, Seymour/photocopies of images from book, undated
  - Towns/Ellington/Farmers/Dobkin-Levine family (Levine & Levine), 1907, original is in Oversize I, People/Farmers, undated
  - Towns/Hebron, Lebanon, Colchester/miscellaneous scenes/not labeled, 1996, undated
  - Towns/Ellington/Rashell and Cantor Farm (Thelma Eisenberg), undated
  - Towns/Farmington/Farmers/Greenberg family farm, undated
  - Towns/Farmington/Farmers/Greenberg, Abraham Leon (1847-1907), undated
  - Towns/Lebanon/Farmers/Schwartz, Mr., feeding chickens, 1946, undated
  - Towns/Lebanon/Farmers/Simon, Leon and Schwartz, Sam, with hay load, undated
  - Towns/Lebanon/Farmers/Simon Family, filed with OVERSIZE photos, undated
  - Towns/Lebanon/Farmers/Simon, Malchen, 1946, undated
  - Towns/Lebanon/Local Community/Synagogue, 1946, undated
  - Towns/Lebanon/Lebanon Historical Society Exhibit, 2000s, undated
  - Towns/Lisbon/Farms/Sadek farm, undated
  - Towns/Moodus/Banner Lodge postcards, undated
  - Towns/Rocky Hill and Wethersfield/Farmers/Selvin Family, slides, c. 1900-1940s, undated
  - Towns/West Hartford-Simsbury/Farmers/Merkin family, c. 1929, undated
- Towns/Colchester continued
  - Towns/Colchester/research papers/Feinsilver, Alexander and Lillian/Colchester Yankee Jews After Half a Century, reprinted from Jewish Commentary, July 1955, undated
  - Towns/Colchester/Research Papers/Kline, Dana L. To Begin Again: the Russian Jewish Migration to Connecticut, Connecticut College, 1976. 2 copies., undated
  - Towns/Colchester/Research Papers/Schwartz, Adam. The Settlement and Development of the Jewish Agricultural Community of Colchester Connecticut, No institutional affiliation given, 1986. Several copies., undated
  - Towns/Colchester/Research Papers/Weisman, Seymour S. The Jewish Community of Colchester, CT: A Century of Modern Schtetl Living, Published version and several copies of manuscript submitted to Hadiera Press, 1995. 3 folders., undated
- Towns/Eastern Connecticut/Research papers and Bloomfield - Canton
  - Towns/Research Papers/Schwartz, Adams. The Settlement and Development of the Jewish Agricultural Community of Colchester, Connecticut., undated
  - Towns/Eastern Connecticut/Research Papers/Gordon, Morton L. The History of the Jewish farmer in Eastern Connecticut. Yeshiva University, 1975. Includes Ellington, Rockville, Willimantic, Colombia, Chestnut Hill, Hebron, Lebanon, Amston, Colchester, Moodus, chesterfield, Woodstock, Putnam, Pomfret, Abington, Killingly, Danielson, Brooklyn, Moosup, Plainfield, Jewett City, Norwich, New London, Madison, Guildford, New Haven, and Hartford. 2 copies., 1975-1975
  - Towns/Bloomfield/Oral History/Bercowetz, Irving and Cutler, Belle Bercowetz, (Copaco), 1980, 1980-1980
  - Towns/Buckland/Hartman tobacco farm/article in The Buckland Times, May 1995, 1995-1995
  - Towns/Canton-Collinsville-Rocky Hill/Family History/Kavalier, Helena/Notes, also includes Isaac Goldberg and Lipshitze families, 1988, 1988-1988
  - Towns/Chesterfield/Miscellaneous photocopies, 1901-1915
- Towns E-Z
  - Towns/East Canaan/Family History/Freund, Eugene and Esther/newspaper clipping and correspondence, 1976, 1976-1976
  - Towns/East Lyme/Family History/Wilensky, Leo, 1990s, 1990-2000
  - Towns/Ellington/Family History/Cohen, Harris/Newspaper clipping, 1993, 1993-1993
  - Towns/Ellington/Family History/Dobkin-Levine, undated
  - Towns/Ellington/Newspaper clippings, undated
  - Towns/Ellington/Oral history/interview questionnaire form, blank, n.d., undated
  - Towns/Ellington/Research Papers/Cantor, Debra S. "They Shall Reap in Joy:" the Early Years of the Jewish Farming Community in Ellington, Connecticut, n.d. Folder contains two versions. No institutional affiliation given., undated
  - Towns/Ellington/Research Papers/Raider, Mark. "The Nascent Farming community in Rockville-Vernon-Ellington, CT (1897-1930)", Brandies University, c. 1993. Folder also contains The Rockville Settlement: Jewish Immigrant Farmers in the Connecticut River Valley, 1993, revised version submitted for publication to Connecticut Jewish History., undated
  - Towns/Farmington/Family History/Greenberg-Katz/reminiscences and photocopies compiled by Hariette Greenberg Katz, 1900-1980s, undated
  - Towns/Glastonbury/Advertisement/Goldberg Bros., after 1903, undated
  - Towns/Greenville, Norwich/Family History/Savin, Mikki, "Rivers of Memory", unpublished manuscript, n.d., undated
  - Towns/Lebanon/Miscellaneous material, 1990s-2000s, 1990-2000
  - Towns/Lebanon/Family History/ Julius Rytman, undated
  - Towns/Lebanon/Oral history/Geitheim, Max, 1974, 1974-1974
  - Towns/Lebanon/Oral history/Major, Marianne, 2006, 2006-2006
  - Towns/Lebanon/Oral history/Major, Marianne, 2006, 2006-2006
  - Towns/Lebanon/Research papers/Hypes, James Lowell/Social Participation in a Rural New England Town, Teachers College, Colombia University, 1927, undated
  - Towns/Lisbon/Family History/Botnick, Ethel S., 1994. Also mentions: Rothenberg, Harry; Goldberg, Morris; Deutsch family; Polinsky, Samuel; Krasofsky family; Cohen family; Sussman’s farm; Berkman's farm; Siedman, Abe., 1994-1994
  - Towns/Lisbon/Miscellaneous materials, 1990s, 1990-2000
  - Towns/Manchester/Rashall, Hyman/newspaper clippings, 1980s, 1980-1990
  - Towns/Mansfield/Miscellaneous materials, 1990s, 1990-2000
  - Towns/Mansfield Center/family history/Seplowitz (poultry farmer), undated
  - Towns/Moodus/Miscellaneous, undated
  - Towns/Morris /Miscellaneous materials compiled by Elaine Rothman, Archivist at Morris Historical Society, 1993, 1993-1993
  - Towns/New Britain/Miscellaneous materials/1890s-1990s, 1890-1990
  - Towns/New Haven/research papers/Wessel, Paul/Jewish Immigrant radicalism in Early 20th Century New Haven, talk given to New Haven Jewish Historical Society, 1988, undated
  - Towns/Newtown/Local Community/Adath Israel Synagogue/Reminiscences by Helen Katzman, 1993, 1993-1993
  - Towns/Norfolk/Newspaper clippings, undated
  - Towns/Norwich/Oral history/Hofner, Kurt, 2006
  - Towns/Rocky Hill-Wethersfield/Family History/Applebaum, Jacob and Rose, undated
  - Towns/Simsbury/Family History/Epstein, Louis/newspaper clipping, 1987
  - Town/Simsbury/Rosedale Farms, undated
  - Towns/South Windsor/Family History/Cohen, Harry/Cohen's Greenhouses, undated
  - Towns/Storrs/Agricultural Club, Inc., flyer for Ninth Annual Fair and Barnstorming, 1925
  - Towns/Suffield/Family History/Stroh, Charles/obituary, 1993
  - Towns/West Hartford-Simsbury/Family History/Merkin/photocopies of miscellaneous documents, undated
  - Towns/Windsor/Family History/Rappaport (Walt and Bond Tobacco Processors, undated
  - National
    - National/American Jewish Historical Society/Photocopies of documents and other material in the American Jewish Historical Society collection. Includes copies of The Jewish Farmer, undated
    - National/New Jersey/Woodbine, undated
    - National/Published material/Levine, Herman J. and Miller, Benjamin. The American Jewish Faming in changing Times. The Jewish Agricultural Society, 1966., undated
    - National/Published material/Miscellaneous photocopies and originals. The Jewish Farmer, undated
    - National/Miscellaneous, undated
- Farming -- Miscellaneous
  - National (Jewish Faming in the United States, not specific to Connecticut), undated
  - Connecticut State, undated
  - Connecticut Jewish History, planned issue on farming, undated
- Manuscripts and Publications
  - Two notebooks 2"by 4" with notes regarding crops an land in various Connecticut towns, 1915-1916
  - One Notebook 2"x3" noting farm expenses and other expenses, 1914-1920, belonging to S. Hartman
  - Center Stage Players Present Mrs. Mehl and the Chicken Hawk -- An Oral History Theatre Presentation Concerning The Colchester Jewish Experience, 1880-1930, undated
  - Book: The American Jewish Farmer in Changing Times by Herman J. Levine and Benjamin Miller, The Jewish Agricultural Society, Inc 1966, undated
- National
  - National/Colchester/Farmers/The Jewish Farmer, National Museum of American Jewish History owns reproduction of May 1912 cover, original, undated
- Agriculture & Farming Photographs, 1850-1990; 0.5 Cubic feet 1 Box
  - Slides/Duplicates of images of other photos in Farming collection, undated
  - Photos from Connecticut Jewish History, undated
  - Miscellaneous/woman with chickens, generic, undated
  - Connecticut Jewish History/Photographs for planned issue on farming, undated